Finding Aid for David Noel Freedman Papers 1932-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Freedman, David Noel (1922-2008) 1932-1983
Freedman, David Noel, 1922-
Biblical scholar, professor of Near Eastern Studies, and director of the Program on Studies in Religion at the University of Michigan. Subject files relating to his scholarly and organizational activities, notably with the American Schools of Oriental Research and as editor of the journal Biblical Archeologist; class notes from courses at Johns Hopkins, including courses taught by William F. Albright; and material concerning his personal and professional relationship with Albright (and Albright's literary estate).
861025 Aa 2
10 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The first accession (boxes 1-7) came from the University of Michigan Program on Studies in Religion (donor nos. 7106 and 9733 ) in September 1984. The second accession (boxes 8-10) came from the same donor in May 2006.
The collection is open for research.
David Noel Freedman is a member of the generation of Biblical scholars influenced by the teachings of William F. Albright, professor of Semitic languages at Johns Hopkins University. Their work has been characterized by the application of linguistic and archeological evidence to Biblical texts.
Freedman was born in 1922 in New York City to Jewish parents, David and Beatrice Freedman. After attending classes at City College of New York from 1935-1938, Freedman continued his studies and received his B.A. from U.C.L.A. in 1939. He then entered the Princeton Theological Seminary and was ordained a Presbyterian minister in 1944. For one year, between 1944-1945, he served as pastor at Acme and Deming in Washington. In 1945, he returned to school, earning his PhD from Johns Hopkins University in 1948. It was while a student at Johns Hopkins that Freedman met F.W. Albright. This marked the start of a friendship and a professional relationship which would continue until Albright's death in 1971, and which would have an important influence on Freedman's development as a scholar.
Upon receiving his doctorate in 1948, Freedman was appointed professor of Hebrew and Old Testament Literature at Western Theological Seminary in Pittsburgh. In 1960, he joined the faculty of the Pittsburgh Theological Seminary, where he taught until 1964. In that year, he moved to the San Francisco Bay area, where he served on the faculty of two institutions. He was professor of the Old Testament at the Graduate Theological Union at Berkeley from 1964-1971. During the same period, he taught courses in the Old Testament and Hebrew exegesis at the San Francisco Theological Seminary, where he also served as Dean of the Faculty from 1966 to 1970, and as Acting Dean of the Seminary in 1970-1971. In 1971, the University of Michigan secured his services as professor of Near Eastern Studies, and as director of the Program on Studies in Religion.
Freedman has been active in a number of organizations. He is a member of the Society of Biblical Literature, a past president of that body (1975-1976) and editor of their Journal of Biblical Literature from 1952 to 1959. He served as director of the Albright Institute for Archaeological Research in Jerusalem in 1969-1970 and 1976-1978. His role in the American Schools of Oriental Research has been especially active. He served as vice-president from 1970-1982, and as director of publications from 1974-1982. This organization sponsors a number of publications, including the Bulletin of the American Schools of Oriental Research, of which Freedman was editor from 1974-1978 and the Biblical Archeologist of which he was editor from 1976-1982.
Perhaps his most ambitious project has been the ongoing editorship of the Anchor Bible, which he assumed in 1956. This publication is made up of translations, with extensive commentary, of various books of the Bible. It represents a collaboration of Catholic, Protestant and Jewish scholars and is unique for its nonsectarian and scholarly analysis of Biblical texts.
David Noel Freedman died April 8, 2008.
Freedman's papers document his research and professional activities, most notably editing the journal Biblical Archeologist, and graduate studies under noted biblical scholar F.W. Albright. The papers have been divided into ten series: Subject Files, the Anchor Bible, the Genesis Project, the Religious Films Development Project, the Task Force on Biblical Authority, Class Notes, William F. Albright, Topical File, Michigan Quarterly Review, and Correspondence.
Subjects:
American Schools of Oriental Research.; Archaeology.; Bible--Criticism, interpretation, etc.; Bible. English. Anchor Bible. 1964.; Bible--Evidences, authority, etc.; Biblical archaeologist.; Genesis Project, Inc.; Johns Hopkins University.; Religion.; Religious Films Development Project.; Task Force on Biblical Authority.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Near Eastern Studies.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Program on Studies in Religion.
Contributors:
Albright, William Foxwell, 1891-1971.
- Subject Files 1977-1982
  The Subject Files, which are in alphabetical order and cover the period 1977-1982, chiefly reflect Freedman's involvement with the American Schools of Oriental Research. The files include incoming and outgoing correspondence, as well as memoranda and minutes. Centered around the time period when Freedman was editor of the Biblical Archeologist, the files contain a great deal of material documenting his involvement with the journal and the activities of his editorial staff. During this same time period, A.S.O.R.'s Committee on Publications, of which Freedman was chairman, decided to withdraw from a publishing consortium called Scholars Press and to produce its publications locally. There is interesting material documenting financial and editorial pressures leading to this decision. other files contain correspondence on controversial topics, such as the archeological discoveries at Ebla or the debate surrounding the Shroud of Turin.
  - Advertising (Box 1)
  - Albright Institute for Archaeological Research Director's Reports (Box 1)
  - American Schools of Oriental Research
    - Agreement with University Microfilms (Box 1)
    - Ancient Manuscript Committee
      - General (Memos, Minutes, etc.) (Box 1)
      - Dead Sea Scrolls (Frank Cross) (Box 1)
      - Dead Sea Scrolls Project (Box 1)
      - Dead Sea Scrolls Publicity (Box 1)
    - Annuals (Box 1)
    - Archeological Expedition Information (Box 1)
    - Board of Trustees
      - General (Box 1)
      - Meeting December 19-22, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Books, Dissertations, etc. (Box 1)
    - Budget (Box 1)
    - Bulletin of the American Schools of Oriental Research (Box 1)
    - Business (Box 1)
    - Committee on Publications
      - 1978-October 1979 (Box 1)
      - November 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - Corporate Representatives (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - A-E (Box 1)
      - F-J (Box 1)
      - K-O (Box 1)
      - P-T (Box 1)
      - U-Z (Box 1)
    - Council of American Overseas Research Center (Box 1)
    - Current (Box 1)
    - Development (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee
      - 1982 (Box 1)
      - 1981 (Box 1)
      - Meeting December 7, 1981 (Box 1)
      - Meeting September 14, 1981 (Box 1)
      - Meeting September 3, 1980 (Box 1)
      - Meeting September 5, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Financial Statements 1979-1982 (Box 2)
    - Meeting
      - April 27, 1981 (Box 2)
      - December 19-22, 1981 (Box 2)
      - May 4-5, 1980 (Box 2)
      - November 6, 1980 (Box 2)
      - November 14-18, 1979 (Box 2)
      - November 17-20, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Minutes and Memorandums 1978 (Box 2)
    - Newsletter 1968-1980 (Box 2)
    - Publications
      - General, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Budget (Box 2)
      - Reports 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - Recruitment (Box 2)
    - Society of Biblical Literature
      - Meeting December 19-22, 1981 (Box 2)
      - Meeting November 5-9, 1980 (Box 2)
      - Meeting February 26-28, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Staff (Box 2)
    - Subscription Services Report (Box 2)
    - Wright Memorial (Box 2)
  - Biblical Archeologist (journal)
    - American Schools of Oriental Research Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Authors 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    - Business (Box 3)
    - Campbell (American School of Oriental Research Archeological Symposium) (Box 3)
    - Editorial (Box 3)
    - Eisenbrauns, correspondence with (Box 3)
    - General Correspondence
      - A-D (Box 3)
      - E-G (Box 3)
      - H-L (Box 3)
      - M-N (Box 3)
      - O-R (Box 3)
      - Sa-Shee (Box 3)
      - Shef-Sz (Box 3)
      - T-Z (Box 3)
    - Material (Box 3)
    - Promotion (Box 3)
    - Qadmoniot (Box 3)
    - Reader IV (Box 3)
  - Beale, Thomas (Box 3)
  - Biblical Archaeology Review (Box 3)
  - Biggs, Robert (Box 3)
  - Blacker, Irwin (Box 3)
  - Borowski visit November 17, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Bortin, Virginia (Box 4)
  - Callaway, Joseph (Box 4)
  - Campbell, E.F./American Schools of Oriental Research Task Force (Box 4)
  - Charlesworth, James H.
    - General (Box 4)
    - Monograph (Box 4)
  - Cohen, I.L. (Box 4)
  - Cohen, Rudolph (Box 4)
  - Conference in Israel 1979 (Box 4)
  - Corner, George (Box 4)
  - Crisler, Cobbey (Box 4)
  - Cross, Frank (Box 4)
  - Cutter/Sackler/Sonnenreich (Box 4)
  - Dahood, Mitchell (Box 4)
  - Dever, William (Box 4)
  - Dothan, Moshe (Box 4)
  - Drinkard, Joel (Box 4)
  - Ebla and the Old Testament (Box 4)
  - Eisenbraun and Japan Symposium (Box 4)
  - Filas, Francis L. (Box 4)
  - Fowler, Harry (Box 4)
  - Frank, H. Thomas
    - 1980 (Box 4)
    - 1979 (Box 4)
    - 1978 (Box 4)
  - Frerichs, Ernest (Box 4)
  - Geraty, Lawrence (Box 4)
  - Glock, Albert (Box 4)
  - Graesser, Carl (Box 4)
  - Greenfield, Jonas (Box 4)
  - Hachlili, Rachel (Box 4)
  - Har-El, Menashe (Box 4)
  - Heldruf Publications (Box 4)
  - Hesi Volume Books (Box 4)
  - Jackson, Mame (Box 4)
  - King/Estey/Misner (Box 4)
  - King, Phil (Box 4)
  - Kochavi, Moshe (Box 4)
  - Landsverk, O.G. (Box 4)
  - Leichty, Erle (Box 4)
  - Maloney, Paul C. (Box 4)
  - Matthiae, Paolo (Box 4)
  - Meyers, Carol and Eric (Box 5)
  - Millard, A.R. (Box 5)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Naveh, Joseph (Box 5)
  - Oren, E.D. (Box 5)
  - Owen, G. Frederick (Box 5)
  - Pope, Marvin (Box 5)
  - Porten, Bezalel (Box 5)
  - Rahmani, L.Y. (Box 5)
  - Rast, Walter (Box 5)
  - Said, Munira (Box 5)
  - Sardis Newsletter (Box 5)
  - Scholars Press
    - Business (Box 5)
    - Denver meeting October 28-30, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Financial 1975-1979 (Box 5)
    - Flanagan, James (Box 5)
    - Funk, Robert (Box 5)
    - General Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Withdrawal 1978 (Box 5)
  - Shea, William (Box 5)
  - Sox, H. David (Box 5)
  - Trustees and potential ones (Box 5)
  - Tuttle, Gary (Box 5)
  - Van Hatten, Willem C. (Box 5)
  - Weinstein, James M. (Box 5)
  - Whallon, William (Box 5)
  - Williams, Prescott (Box 5)
- Anchor Bible 1855-1983
  The Anchor Bible series contains Freedman's correspondence between 1955 and 1983 with three of his editors: Joseph A. Fitzmeyer, editor of the Gospel of Luke, Jonathan Goldstein, editor of Maccabees, and P. Kyle McCarter, editor of Samuel. Freedman's detailed notes and suggestions on translation, and his editorial commentaries on the analysis of difficult passages are extremely interesting.
  The files grouped under the 1965-1977 heading, part of the 2006 accession, contain correspondence between Freedman and the various contributors for the Anchor Bible Series. Some material is not dated and may fall outside the specified date range. The Anchor Bible Series is a series of retranslations of Old Testament biblical texts with notes and commentaries on the translation. The bulk of the material consists of comments, notes, and corrections by Freedman of the manuscripts submitted for publication. While many of the corrections are trivial, Freedman also gives a large amount of commentary expressing his opinions and thoughts about the ancient texts and appropriate translations. The folders are organized alphabetically by the manuscript author's last name.
  - Fitzmeyer, Joseph A. II Luke, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Goldstein, Jonathan II Maccabees, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - McCarter, P. Kyle II Samuel, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - 1965-1977
    - Albright and Mann-Matthew (Box 10)
    - Boling -- Judges (Box 10)
    - Brown -- John I & II (Box 10)
    - Buchanan -- Hebrews (Box 10)
    - [Caine-] Genesis (Box 10)
    - [McKenzie -- II Isaiah] (Box 10)
    - Moore -- Esther (Box 10)
    - Pope -- Job, Song of Songs (Box 10)
    - Walter -- I Corinthians (Box 10)
- Genesis Project
  The Genesis Project is a commercial, educational firm for which the Program on Studies in Religion served in an advisory capacity. The project documented here is the transcription of four seminars which occurred between December 1974 and March 1975 and involved Freedman and other religious scholars. Two of the seminars dealt with the story of Abraham, one with the New Testament, and one with the stories of John the Baptist and the Nativity. It is the transcriptions, with penciled-in corrections, which make up this series.
  - General (Box 6)
  - Transcripts
    - New Testament Seminar December 11, 1974 (Box 6)
    - Nativity/John the Baptist Seminar February 10, 1975 (Box 6)
    - Abraham Seminar February 11, 1975 (Box 6)
    - Abraham Seminar March 20, 1975 (Box 6)
- Religious Films Development Project
  The series on the Religious Films Development Project contains correspondence with officers of the Lilly Endowment, which funded the project from June 1976 through June 1977. At least two television films were produced under the auspices of the Project: Jacob and Joseph and The Story of David. Freedman acted in an advisory capacity for both films, to ensure historical accuracy in such details as costume and language. The series contains a partial script of Jacob and Joseph and the full script of The Story of David as well as publicity materials.
  - Lilly Endowment
    - General June 1976-June 1977 (Box 6)
    - Alberg, Mildred (Box 6)
    - Lecky, Robert (Box 6)
  - Jacob and Joseph (proposed film: partial script) (Box 6)
  - Story of David (proposed film)
    - Part I: David-and King Saul (script) (Box 6)
    - Part II: David the King (script) (Box 6)
    - Newsclippings, publicity (Box 6)
- Task Force On Biblical Authority
  Freedman was a member of the Presbyterian Church's Task Force on Biblical Authority in 1981-1982. The series concerning this task force contains the final version of the report, and two longer drafts, as well as material from the various meetings of the Task Force. These materials include correspondence, minutes and notes.
  - Report (Box 7)
  - Meetings
    - January 7-9, 1982 (San Diego) (Box 7)
    - December 3-4, 1981 (Cincinnati) (Box 7)
    - October 8-10, 1981 (Newark) (Box 7)
    - April 23-25, 1981 (Princeton) (Box 7)
    - January 2-4, 1981 (Denver) (Box 7)
- Class Notes 1945-1949
  The series of Freedman's Class Notes date from 1945-1949, the years he was a doctoral student at Johns Hopkins. There are a number of course notes which trace his progression through several Biblical languages, including Arabic and Aramaic. Freedman also took many courses on Oriental art and archaeology which were offered by W.F. Albright, as well as seminars on cultural history taught by Albright.
  - 1945
    - Archaeology (Box 7)
    - Synthesis of Israelite Culture (Box 7)
  - 1945-1946
    - Ancient History (Box 7)
  - 1946
    - Ancient Oriental Archaeology (Box 7)
    - Arabic (Box 7)
    - Assyrian (Box 7)
    - Cultural and Religious History from Solomon to Exile (Box 7)
  - 1946-1947
    - Ancient Oriental History (Box 7)
    - Comparative Semitic Grammar (Box 7)
    - Hebrew Syntax (Box 7)
  - 1947
    - Arabic (Box 7)
    - Archaeology (Box 7)
    - Babylonian Aramaic (Box 7)
    - Toward a Synthesis of Israelite Culture (Box 7)
  - 1947-1948
    - Ancient Oriental Archaeology and Art (Box 7)
    - Ancient Oriental History (Box 7)
    - Aramaic Inscriptions (Box 7)
    - Biblical Aramaic (Box 7)
    - Hebrew Phonology (Box 7)
    - Semitic Grammar (Box 7)
  - 1948-1949
    - Old Testament History (Box 7)
  - Undated
    - Assyrian (Box 7)
    - Assyrian II (Box 7)
    - Books of Samuel (Box 7)
    - Deuteronomy: Rapid Reading (Box 7)
    - Genesis (Box 7)
    - Kings: Rapid Reading (Box 7)
    - Notes (Box 7)
    - Old Testament Theology (Box 7)
- William F. Albright 1945-1975
  The William F. Albright Series, 1945-1975 consists mostly of material (typically correspondence) relating to Albright posthumously and a large amount consists of correspondence between Freedman and Albright. Freedman assisted in executing Albright's literary estate, the compiling and editing of a comprehensive Albright Bibliography and a Biography of Albright. The materials are organized into three sub series: Background, Bibliography, and Correspondence. The Background subseries consists of obituary material written by Freedman about Albright and related material written by multiple authors giving biographical information about Albright. The sub series also includes material documenting the executing of Albright's literary estate. The Bibliography subseries consists of correspondence relating to the compiling and publishing of a comprehensive Albright Bibliography. The majority of the Correspondence subseries is made up of correspondence between Freedman and Albright for the majority of their acquaintance. It begins with a response from Albright to a letter of introduction written by Freedman in 1945, and continues as the two men develop relationships as mentor/mentee, colleagues, co-workers, and friends. There is a small amount of correspondence between 1945 and 1949, after which time the correspondence begins to increase in frequency and length. While there is evidence of a close relationship between the two men's families, the correspondence maintains a very professional tone and subject matter. The remainder of the sub series contains correspondence between Freedman and various individuals about Albright, Albright projects, and reminiscence about Albright. Some of the folders contain copies of correspondence between the various individuals and Albright, which were sent to Freedman after Albright's death. The latter correspondence relates mostly to the executing of Albright's estate, and contain a signed copy of the legal agreement between the Albright heirs and the Albright Institute which established the group responsible for executing Albright's literary estate.
  - Background
    - Obituary/Biography
      - Obituary Articles (Box 8)
      - Memorial Notice, BASOR (Box 8)
      - William Foxwell Albright, [New Catholic Encyclopedia Article] (Box 8)
      - Transcript: "Three-hour conversation at Frank Cross' home, Lexington, Mass. May 13, 1972 with him, G. Ernest Wright, Ted Campbell, and Noel Freedman." (Box 8)
      - Mrs. Albright to G. E. Wright [Ruth Reminiscence of the "American School"] (Box 8)
      - Albright Letter [Intent to write Albright Biography] (Box 8)
    - Literary Estate
      - Manuscript (Box 8)
        (Correspondence concerning the printing of Albright's previously unpublished "History of Religion in Israel" posthumously.)
      - Publication Fund (Box 8)
      - Publications (Box 8)
      - Responses to Requests for the Reprinting of Albright Articles (Box 8)
    - Bibliography (Box 8)
    - W.F. Albright Bibliography Project, General File (Box 8)
    - Re: W. F. Albright Publication (Box 8)
    - Braun-Brumfield, Albright Bibliography (Box 8)
    - Albright Bibliography (Box 8)
  - Correspondence
    - Albright, W. F. 1945-1971 [between Albright and Freedman], 7 folders (Box 8)
    - Albright -- General, 3 folders (Box 8)
      (Correspondence between Freedman and various individuals concerning remembrances of Albright and Albright's Literary Estate)
    - Albright, David F. (Box 8)
    - Bloomhardt, P. F. (Box 8)
      (includes photocopies of correspondence between W. F. Albright and Bloomhardt)
    - [Fensham, Charles] (Box 8)
      (includes photocopies of correspondence between W. F. Albright and Fensham)
- Topical File 1955-1978
  The Topical Files Series, 1955-1978 contains material concerning several projects and organizations in which Freedman participated. It includes research projects, periodicals, publications, the Michigan University Press, the Michigan State Board of Education and the Council on the Study of Religion. The Council on the Study of Religion (CSR) is comprised of several smaller organizations and Freedman was very active in a few of them. The Council on the Study of Religion subseries contains material relating to his activities in the larger organization and in these sub organizations: the Council on the Study of Religion in Michigan Public Schools and the American Academy of Religion. A few folders in the CSR subseries pertain to the publishing of a book for the American Academy of Religion based on a set of lectures given at a weekend conference organized by Freedman for the Program in Studies on Religion at the University of Michigan.
  - Applications for Research Grants (Box 8)
  - Association for American Colleges (Box 8)
  - Freedman-Cross Archaeological Project
    - Achziv (Box 8)
  - Bible Computer Project, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Council on the Study of Religion
    - Council on the Study of Religion (Box 9)
    - American Academy of Religion Meeting -- October 4-6th, Correspondence (Box 9)
    - Big Ten Meeting -- January 22, 1973 Agenda and Minutes (Box 9)
    - Big Ten Meeting -- January 22, 1973 Correspondence (Box 9)
    - Council on the Study of Religion in Michigan Public Schools
      - 1971-1975, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Materials from Conference of March 21-22, 1972, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Religion and the American Academic Scene
      - Bellah, Robert (Box 9)
      - Correspondence (Box 9)
      - Panel (Box 9)
  - [Journal of Biblical Literature] (Box 9)
  - [Lilly Endowment Proposal, Correspondence] (Box 9)
  - Michigan State and West Michigan Requests for Approval for Teaching Cert. Programs 1973 (Box 9)
  - "The People's Choice, a play by David Freedman" circa 1932 (Box 10)
    (photo copy)
  - University of Michigan Press Correspondence (Box 9)
- Michigan Quarterly Review 1982-1983
  The Michigan Quarterly Review Series, 1982-1983 concerns the production of a special issue of the Michigan Quarterly Review (a University of Michigan scholarly journal) about biblical topics which Freedman co-edited with Michael Patrick O'Connor. The Topical subseries is a set of correspondence folders documenting the general process of coordinating the editing and publication of that journal issue. The Correspondence subseries contains folders of correspondence between the various contributors to the issue and Freedman and/or O'Connor.
  - Topical
    - General (Box 9)
    - MS Logs (Box 9)
    - University Publications (Box 9)
    - Unlabeled (Box 9)
  - Correspondence
    - Avision, Margaret (Box 9)
    - Band, Arnold (Box 9)
    - Baskin (Leonard) Artwork (Box 9)
    - Blamires, David (Box 9)
    - Brand, John (Box 9)
    - Chagall (Marc) Artwork (Box 9)
    - Coffin, Edna (Box 9)
    - Collins, John (Box 9)
    - Crossan, J.D. (Box 9)
    - Davis, William Virgil (Box 9)
    - Fink, Robert (Box 9)
    - Freedman, David (Box 9)
    - Frymer-Kensky, Tikva (Box 9)
    - Huffmon, Herb (Box 9)
    - Kavanagh, Aidan (Box 9)
    - Kirkpatrick (Box 9)
    - Levine, Baruch (Box 9)
    - Libolt, Clayton (Box 9)
    - Martyn, J. Louis (Box 9)
    - McGinn, Bernard (Box 9)
    - Meyers, Carol (Box 9)
    - Moore, Jim (Box 9)
    - Neusner, Jack (Box 9)
    - O'Conner, Michael (Box 10)
    - Oresick, Peter (Box 10)
    - Rasco, Karen (Box 10)
    - Rubenstein, Richard (Box 10)
    - Stafford, Bill (Box 10)